[Music]
all right hello and welcome everyone
it is actin flab live stream number 36.0
and it's january 13th 2022.
welcome to the actin flap we are a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve on our
work and also if you're watching along
live please write any comments or
questions you have in the live chat all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
here and we'll be following good video
etiquette for live streams and thanks
blue for
helping a lot with the slides and for
coming on because this will be a fun
comp up
go to activeinference.org to learn more
about how to participate in any of the
lab activities or bring some new idea to
the lab
okay
here we are in
live stream number 36 in the second half
of january 2022
and the goal is to learn and discuss
this paper by matt sims and giovanni
pizzulo from 2021 the paper is called
modeling ourselves what the free energy
principle reveals about our implicit
notions of representation
and
as with all zero videos the video is an
introduction for some of the ideas and a
hasty review
so it's not a review or a final word
we're going to have the upcoming two
weeks to talk more about this paper and
hopefully talk to some of the authors or
any other people who are interested in
this idea
and
get involved if you want to talk about
the paper so let's just start with
saying hello and an introduction and
then what we were excited to read about
the paper i'm daniel i'm in california
and was excited to
read yet another paper on
representations and the fep because it
feels like we had a stretch back there
of
five in a row or something
what about you blue
i'm blue i'm in new mexico and um i
really enjoyed matt sims paper on
symbiosis that we did a while ago and i
thought this paper was really neat and
um really a clear elucidation of
the different categories of
representation and how like there's
overarching like representation and
non-representation and then several
different layers within that so i
thought it broke it down in a really
clear and concise way um even though
it's a lot of material to digest
do you want to ask the big question
sure the big question of the article was
can the free energy principle help us
advance or even resolve the long-lasting
debate on internal representation in
philosophy of mind
it's a long lasting debate so this is
like the dot zero of dot zeros because
it's clearly a topic you could spend a
lot of time on so
that's our disclaimer is uh
it's a long-standing debate
but here's kind of a meme slide so it's
uh the first section of this paper
right below the title
it has this quotation from walt whitman
and it says hold it up sternly see this
it sends back
who is it is it you
and uh then here are several different
images
and
just think about your perception of
these images and the cultural
significance that you might attach to
them or the way that black and white
pixels or gray pixels on a screen give
the illusion of depth or remind you of
an experience that you've never had so
that's kind of trippy and representation
gets at some of those
issues
that's one non-philosophical take on it
what are they going to aim to do in this
debate which we're going to sketch out
the sides of in
uh
this talk
or i guess this discussion um
do you want to read it blue or tell me
sure so
the authors argue that even if the fep
can't solve this long-standing debate
it can play an invaluable role in
revealing our hidden assumptions about
the very notion of representation
and can create some common ground to
discuss and negotiate them
so they say our general strategy is to
use the fep for conceptual clarification
of different notions of representation
we work backwards from representational
or non-representational interpretations
of the fep's constructs to the various
notions of representation that motivate
those interpretations
so they claim that it emerges from their
analysis that the fep has been or can be
used to implement various kinds of
computational models which satisfy the
requirements of certain theories of
representation hence the question of
whether or not the fep entails
representations depends on what notion
of representation one uses in the first
place
we're going to unpack that a lot but
just wanted to give the first coat of
paints on what they're aiming and what
they claim to do
so i'll read the first half of the
abstract
predictive processing theories are
increasingly popular in philosophy of
mind such process theories often gain
support from the free energy principle
fep a normative principle for adaptive
self-organized systems
yet there is a current and much
discussed debate about conflicting
philosophical interpretations of fep
for example representational versus
non-representational
here we argue that these different
interpretations depend on implicit
assumptions about what qualifies or
fails to qualify as representational
the next part
we deploy the fep instrumentally to
distinguish four main notions of
representation which focus on
organizational structural content
related and functional aspects
respectively the various ways that these
different aspects matter in arriving at
representation or non-represent
representational interpretations of the
fep are discussed we also discuss how
the fep may be seen as a unified view
where terms that traditionally belong to
different ontologies for example
notions of model and expectation versus
notions of autopoiesis and
synchronization can be harmonized
however rather than attempting to settle
the representationalist versus
non-representationalist debate and
reveal something about what
representations are simplicitor this
paper demonstrates how the free energy
principle may be used to reveal
something about those partaking in the
debate namely what are hidden
assumptions about what representations
are assumptions that act as sometimes
antithetical starting points in this
persistent philosophical debate
so there's really two
or three pieces to this paper
there's an introduction and
an abstract i guess we can delete that
um the first part introduces a short
summary on the free energy principle
and we'll see that
action
perception cognition loop
the bulk of the paper is in these four
segments of each with a dyadic
relationship of the representational and
the non-representational perspectives
and that section is a lot like a
literature review and a philosophical
taxonomy
of different perspectives and arguments
related to representation and fep and
these four subdivisions
there's then a
addendum on evolutionary function
specifically and
that's apt as
nothing in biology makes sense except in
the light of evolution as they say
and then section 5 kind of turns a
mirror back on
the process and thought
just like those earlier images with the
mirror
and that's where fep
differences in perspective are used
almost as input data for
theorizing and speculating about
different things which we'll get to so
that takes the authors then to the
conclusion it's a pretty wide-ranging
paper
and the keywords that are
here are active inference free energy
principle predictive processing
generative model internal representation
action-oriented representation
inactivism
forward model and markov blankets
there's no single path or single slide
that would do justice to all these
keywords so we're just going to kind of
jump in
and knowing that some people will be
really familiar with some of these terms
and others will be hearing about them
for the first time
so first the big topic is representation
now this is just a
quote from the paper whether
or not living organisms have or need
internal representations is an old and
fiercely debated topic
so we kind of like
unzipped that citation to add the titles
and the links and just some of the
images from these
citations so if these topics or any of
this
body of literature you feel like is well
motivated or
well reasoned or you've never been
exposed to it that's sort of the
continent we're on
and it is such a large continent so the
authors write such a debate is
reiterated within the predictive
processing view so they're going to tell
the story of representation from
predictive processing as sort of a
implicit
starting point
from a more specific and mechanistic
angle i.e assuming the fep is a good
model of living organisms does it entail
the notion of internal representation or
not so it's almost like we're
conditioning our analysis whether it's a
counterfactual or not
on fep being used instrumentally
so we're going to use it just like we
would use a ruler not by questioning the
ruler against known objects but by going
to unknown objects and investigating
them so that's the way that the fep is
going to be used in this very large
scale
topic
and complex area of representation
any comments blue
alright
another big topic and word that comes up
in this paper but also a lot of other of
our discussions is inactivism
and so who better to hear it from
than the radicals so
herrick 2014 i think it's a
thesis
why radical inactivism is not radical
enough a case for really radical and
activism so take it up with the author
if this is oversimplifying or that's
kind of the joke slash
appeal here it is oversimplifying and
here we see three different
uh frameworks contrasted against each
other
cognitivism
radical and activism and then really
radical in activism and
cognitivism differs from an activism on
the top row in that cognitivism says
basic cognition is representational and
an activism is going to be
rejecting that claim on all accounts
and then where this author is saying
that you could even go further
into the inactive camp or forest or
whatever
is you could even deny that linguistic
cognition
is representational so even if it looks
symbolic
and it looks like it has some
representational characteristic and it's
the gray zone that makes people go oh
okay maybe there is some redeeming
aspect of representation you just have
to keep on denying it so
maybe we can pick that thread up again
but that's sort of the lay of the land
of maybe the uh center and activists the
moderates and then the extremists
blew anything down
no it's so interesting to really think
about about representation and the brain
i mean coming from neuroscience actually
okay i'll add something coming from
neuroscience it's interesting to really
think about
um i mean the visual cortex is very
unique in the sense that we like know
that there's representation that is
replicated in the brain um but
everywhere else it's just kind of like
you know we've never found like the word
for apple in the brain somewhere like
there's no like apple neuron so so it's
just an interesting
i don't know just a juxtaposition i
guess about representation and language
um
thinking about it in terms of the brain
also one really
important aspect that we didn't mention
is it's about action like it is
basically saying that action is
it's related to embodiment and all these
other things but inactivism is just
focusing on action and what that means
um
all right free energy principle which
we're going to spend
a lot of the discussion on
it's an integrative prince proposal on
adaptive self-organizing systems that
remain far from thermodynamic
equilibrium
so that would be cool if we had one
common framework for things that maybe
were
far or close to equilibrium currently we
only have some of those areas of face
space
it starts from the premise that in order
to survive living organisms engage in
reciprocal action perception exchanges
with their environment
they must do what they can in order to
remain within a neighborhood of viable
states
that's kind of the cybernetic regulator
insight
then the bottom paragraph
the idea is cast in bayesian terms by
assuming that ecologically adaptive
states constitute the priors of the
agents
the states that an agent prefers to
visit become the states that it expects
to visit
hence minimizing surprise or its
long-term average which is entropy
becomes
a primary imperative for living
organisms as it prevents them or permits
them to counteract an otherwise
unavoidable process of dispersion and
loss of integrity which kind of closes
the loop back with the resistance to
dissipation that was brought up in the
beginning
so this is kind of one fep boomerang
from starting with a focus on resisting
dissipation and then moving through the
action and perception loop
to ecological preferences and back to
the reduction of uncertainty and thus
resisting dissipation
a partitioning that is
natural
or at least complementary to the fep is
the markov blanket partitioning
uh
we've talked about this in several other
streams so we won't go into it in too
much detail this is from 26
and
the
markov blanket condition at least in its
uh more narrow slash technical sense
is referring to some set of nodes
representing statistical variables
and that set of nodes that make up the
blanket make some other sets of nodes
two other sets of nodes which we can
call the internal and external states it
makes those two sets conditionally
independent
and the edges are statistical influence
blue
what else would you say about markov
blankets they say it here beautifully so
the blanket states act as an
informational boundary between internal
and external states and that's like the
simplest way to think about it right
like my skin acts as a barrier between
myself and the world the blanket acts as
a barrier
yes cool
okay
leaving fap land proper
we can
zoom out to some related topics that
sometimes get brought up in discussions
of fep but often don't
so first is the predictive processing
framework
this is drawn from a citation that was
in the bibliography but not sure if it
was in the text highway 2020
and this is a
paper
new directions in predictive processing
so predictive processing asserts that
perceptual and cognitive systems engage
in prediction error minimization
enabling approximate bayesian perceptual
inference
and some but
apparently not all authors
emphasize action so clark and howie
famously and recently have emphasized
that action is essential to predictive
processing in the form of active
inference where the system infers its
own policies
so really
emphasizing that the predictions are not
just about
sensory
inputs
but causes
of sensory input hypotheses about latent
unobserved causes in the world and also
one's own action policies what one
expects to do
and there's a really awesome
supplemental file for this paper that
includes a great literature analysis and
a lot of keywords
and unique uh
predictions and lists of
empirical evidence so this is really
awesome uh work and it'd be great to
hear from people who
study predictive processing or are more
familiar with it
how they see it in relationship to
active inference and fep
something that's
in the overlap of predictive processing
bayesian statistical theories active
inference is the idea of a generative
model
so let's recall
from
dcm
uh the dynamical causal modeling
that uh which we talked about in the
previous
weeks in uh number 35
and
here in dcm it's a
appealing to biologically grounded
models and dynamical systems theory to
create a probabilistic generative model
of hemodynamic fluctuations so what is a
generative model
it's basically opposed to a descriptive
model so why would one use a generative
model in statistics because these types
of models can be run in both directions
they can be fit from data but they can
also be used to generate data
and then they can be used in different
ways because of that capacity
dimensional general
generative models can be very
computationally efficient
because they only have to be updating a
few parameters rather than keeping track
of every single data parameter
and then a little bit more on the
interpretive layer or
beyond the merely statistical
generative models capture some of these
open-ended and creative or complex
dynamics that are associated with action
and perception and cognition
and therefore there are links to
not only the cognitive sciences but also
philosophy and phenomenology
so it's kind of an idea from statistics
that gets connected to some of the
fundamentals of neuroscience and
philosophy
and
uh
anything to add on that blue
yeah so just when i think of the
generative model um
having listened to so many people
describe it my favorite description is
um
almost as like the the recognition model
is more like the hardware or like the
state and then the generative model is
like the software the action between
them or like the dominoes and the like
stacked dominoes and then the cascading
wave right so the dominoes would be the
recognition model and then the
generative model is the relationship
between them the cascading wave of
dominance i always like to to use that
analogy just it's clear for me so
cool
and here's one more slide from 26
where the idea of the mark called
blanket which we pulled from 26 as well
is connected to the idea of a generative
model
in the section on predictive processing
and so in this paper so go check out
number 26 or the paper on bayesian
mechanics to learn more but the idea is
that it's possible to use that markov
blanket partitioning
so that there's the blanket states
statistically
isolating internal and external states
and then there might be some
systems where those partitioned internal
states
are acting as if they are
doing inference on external states
so that would be like if i
said i'm gonna hold up three fingers and
put it behind my back and then you had a
generative model that was about
what was the state of that unobserved
variable
and uh
that's something to look more into from
the details on generative model as with
other papers
and that kind of brings us to our last
keyword which is
active inference
and so we'll go into a little more
detail here
they describe that active inference
agents
are self-evidencing
which is to say that because minimizing
free energy over time is equivalent to
maximizing bayesian model evidence or
self-evidence
in engaging in long-term
active inference agents
seek out or generate those sense sensory
samples that maximize the lower bound on
the evidence for an implicit model of
how their sensory states were generated
as such active inference agents author
evidence for their own continued
existence via free energy minimizing
model optimization
so
active inference is using statistics to
operationalize
some of the information thermodynamic
like formalisms of the fep
so
it'd be a more narrow interpretation
that that carries no or little
philosophical baggage or claims to how
the world really is it would be a more
broad or stronger interpretation to
think that this is capturing the actual
information dynamics or the actual
thermodynamic
relationships of systems but the
instrumental usage is more of a
statistical similarity or at least
attractability
argument
and that is not without precedent not
even close because the variational
bayesian methods which minimize or
optimize this
quantity called the evidence lower bound
start maximizing the
lower bound for how good the evidence is
and
others in many places have motivated
this fundamental
component of modern bayesian statistics
from multiple different areas and it's
kind of like equations are true so
equations can be linked to each other
and it's just kind of cool that these
kl divergences
as well as free energy
and the information or description
length
criterion all align and that's not even
like an active synthesis
applying that to inference on action is
something that is
bringing together a lot of these ideas
from variational bathing methods with a
lot of ideas from control theory
cybernetics inactivism etc and
again
we can explore back and find out which
ideas came from where but just to keep
in mind it's like these pieces were not
tied together by active those are
excellent relationships in the
literature but academ does integrate
the free energy principle and that
center meme that they started with that
things have to resist dissipation
with
all of this philosophy
and more quantitative areas that have to
do with action and perception
and then in the dot one and dot two
we'll go more into
the um variational and expected free
energy but
kind of wanted to just
give a little thought on active
inference and if someone has a different
thought it'd be awesome to hear it as
well but this paper was very precise
and very um
subtle in how it thought about some of
these areas so i think it's really good
to be clear about what we're talking
about
in this case
okay onto the paper
all right
so this is going to be a slow roll of
the introduction
there's a growing consensus in
computational and systems neuroscience
around the idea the brain is a
predictive machine which uses internal
or generative models to continuously
generate predictions in service of
prediction action and learning so
starting with the idea of prediction
second sentence
one of the ways that people are studying
prediction in the brain
is predictive processing so we talked
about that a few minutes ago
the free energy principle is extending
predictive processing
by providing it with a fundamental
principle of adaptive self-organization
that's the resist dissipation meme that
isn't intrinsically within predictive
processing framework which might
describe
audio processing in a radar signal
and so that
union of fep and predictive processing
are starting to become prominent outside
of systems neuroscience
which might seem like their natural
niche or origin
but it's also the case that philosophers
in the philosophy of mind are starting
to think about it
and
despite that attention the authors are
arguing that some of the implications
for fep's uh
existence
remain widely debated i think we can
agree on that
and they're going to focus on one of the
prominent discussions that they think is
the most prominent which is whether the
fep is representational or
non-representational
and then to what extent it is also
bearing on debates related to
internalism
action orientation and activism so just
it's all over the map it's a
multi-dimensional philosophy face space
with the fep
and it's not totally resolved but that's
what they're going to go into in this
paper
okay
the oh yeah blue
so
um
they they note here that philosophical
discussions or representation wars about
the fep have typically been focused on
four aspects of the notion of
representation
so these four aspects are organizational
structural content related or functional
um and
the organizational aspects have some
variable inside a system that's
separated from that which it represents
outside the system
structural aspects have representational
vehicles that are structurally similar
to the state of affairs in the world
that they stand for content related
aspects have internal models that either
encode environmental contingencies or
sensory motor contingencies
specification or description of how the
world is taken to be in turn analyzed in
terms of correctness or truth conditions
and then the functional aspects support
vicarious use before or in the absence
of external events of
internal variables of a model
well
it is kind of a whoa but this four-fold
distinction is the structure of the
paper so we're gonna do a few fun things
to help understand
this because it is the contribution and
the structure of the paper so everyone's
going to interpret all of this in their
own way which is awesome but we do
really want to be clear about what the
author's contributions are
so
in an almost unprecedented maneuver
we're going to go to the end of the
paper first and then also have the
figures out of order
we're going to start with what we can
learn from this debate so if you're not
sure if you want to listen to the next
like 40 minutes on going into this for
full distinction
you get it up front so
they're going to review some of the most
prominent philosophical interpretations
of the fep
they then
summarize
those interpretations according to the
four different categories that blue just
read
for each of those categories they're
going to consider multiple constructs of
fep
so kind of tools in the fep
toolkit ecosystem
and they're going to
argue that depending on which
perspective you take on which of these
categories and which constructs you're
going to come to different conclusions
about the representational or
non-representational nature of the fep
so
it's kind of like a checkerboard
that's their first
salvo
is
we're going to outline a flow chart and
a grid and a structure like a taxonomy
of philosophical ideas related to
this
triple
dimensional space of
aspects of representation
constructs of the fep
and then the categorical variable
representational or non-representational
claims
and then
the whole second part
is saying we're going to use that
three-dimensional phase space
to shine a light on
one's own implicit notions of
representation so that's kind of like
the looking in the mirror
strange loop part but the first part is
more like a philosophical literature
analysis
and their contribution in figure two
is to make this awesome flow chart
so
this is going to funnel you from the
start
in the four different domains four
aspects organizational structural
content and functional
and then from those four starting points
kind of like sorry board
you're going to get funneled
towards
non-representational or representational
fep depending on decisions and that's
what we're going to unpack in the next
sections
because again it's kind of like
trippy and there's a lot to think about
this is going to be our map
so it's going to be at the bottom of all
of the upcoming slides
which of these eight
sections were in it's like a cube
divided in eight
little cubes
or two
tetrahedra or some other pattern but
basically we're gonna see whether we're
in like representation camp or
non-representation camp and which aspect
we're focused on and then here's that
table but it's just the tip of the
iceberg
so
how can we organize
our thinking around philosophy
and increase the rigor
and the accessibility of different
arguments
because it can be difficult sometimes to
parse it in
long texts
and so the authors clearly thought a lot
about this so it's a really um pleasure
to read about it and learn about it
and the flowchart is a great addition so
that is going to be our map in the
coming slides
right now thanks for making such a
beautiful map i have to say like i had
like pasted a whole bunch of these ideas
and tried to like categorize them and
then daniel you know constructed them
into this beautiful flow chart so well
yeah they made the flowchart i made the
grid yep the grid that's what i meant
the grid the grid
before we see the grid in action though
let's just recall this action perception
loop and we're not gonna go into it
right now but that's definitely for a
dot one and dot two
what are these
nodes and edges and
which
can and can't happen and what do they
represent
so
that is sort of the partitioning
that we're going to be working within
which we brought up a little earlier
with the markov blanket and in a lot of
our other discussions
okay so let us start
in this
top left
square
so this is the organizational
aspect the representational perspective
so
the organizational aspect
is uh
describing how variables inside a system
are separated from what it represents
outside the system
so that's like the architectural
take on representations that's i don't
know is it classic representations
but um the pro-representation camp
are going to argue that internal states
are segregated from the external world
via markov blanket
therefore
the brain's activity cast as internal
states
do represent what it doesn't have access
to
blue what do you think
or anything else to add on it
nothing i want to delve into here
because i'm going to save it for that
one okay okay in contrast
there's other people
and other perspectives who
are going to
in the organizational aspect take a
non-representational
and so philosophers of the ecological
and activist persuasion have
approached that same markov blanket
formalism
and basically framed it
in terms of
non-representational view of the fep
like yella bronenberg's paper the
anticipating brain is not a scientist
free energy principle from an ecological
and active perspective
so they argue in those papers in a lot
of papers by yella and others
that
just because you deploy the markov
blanket formalism
it doesn't imply the behavior of the
system is best explained by inferences
generated by an internal model
the structure of which is representing
that which is a model of
so
read the papers for more detail but it's
like
um
it's an interesting idea and it was also
interesting to read in from this paper
that
the
restatement of this argument that
these partially informationally
encapsulated systems like we talked
about in
35 are
parsimoniously understood in terms of
achieving high relative mutual
information
between the non-representational process
of generalized synchrony in huygens 1673
the pendulum clock so you can get like
oscillating pendulums that synchronize
but they don't have representations of
each other
now maybe you need
representations to um
do something else but that kind of gets
to that inactivist radical and activist
debate so we'll go more into it later
just kind of cool
old citation and um
interesting idea so
based upon the organization of the
system there's people who say yeah the
fep is representational of course
because the internal states are isolated
or no because you can get high mutual
information without representation
all right
that's like what what dean called nine
o'clocking
it's nine o'clock that's general
synchrony exactly
there's doesn't need to be a
representation of um brushing the teeth
in the
in the mind or the anything of the
reader
okay
on to the second aspect the structural
aspects so the question to be addressed
is whether generative models are
structurally similar to their targets
or accurate descriptions of external
reality
or
whether models needn't be accurate but
merely adequate enough
to leverage for adaptive behavioral
control
so does it actually need to represent
the thing
or can it be just some other
representation
that
is effective enough
so here's the pro and the con for
representational on one
slide
the top
structural representationalist view
argues that the generative model has to
have some structural resemblance with
the generative process in order to be
useful for control purposes that's
really related to the good regulator
theorem from cybernetics
um
and so
the argument there is you're going to
need the good representation about it
in order to be
on the right page in complex
environments
um
others
disagree
so here's one line of argument that the
formal constructs in active inference
specifically the generative density g
if it's understood correctly according
to some authors it would turn out to be
non-representational
those authors suggested ramp said at all
2019 that generative models do not meet
the requirements of structural
representations
where some internal structure replicates
some structure of a generative process
so the generative model
is the organism's model of action
the generative process is the actual
world out there the niche that's giving
rise to observations and so in other
words you might be
i don't know if this might be a mal
example but like
to run you don't need to have an
abstract representation of your own body
you merely need the
action
interactions with your body
and so this is kind of arguing that the
internal generative density g
inactive doesn't have to have any
resemblance structurally to even the
problem which it's being deployed to
solve
well and this always goes to the map and
the territory and the difference between
the map and the territory so
structural similarity like what does
that mean
right like so so how similar is there
some metric that you're using for
structural similarity like how similar
is the map of the united states to the
actual united states right and so what
what does that even mean structural
similarity sorry like i'm i'm probably
you know
poking the fire but
let's
hear from um
alex keefer or maxwell or anyone else
who feels really strongly about this
issue because we've had some fun talks
on it before and it's just
i just liked seeing the pro and the con
laid out together
and then
the authors were very um
very i just like arguing what is the
difference between the pro and the con i
i want to i want somebody to draw the
line for me what is similar and what is
not similar enough
nice okay now to the third aspect so
this is the content related
aspect
um
whether the generative models
need to explicitly model the ways
external states produce sensations
aka environmental models or the ways
that actions produce sensations or
sensory motor models
this is very closely related to the
previous
aspect so i think it'd be cool to unpack
it a little more but there is a little
bit of nuance
with
sensory motor
systems
which we talked about in several places
like skilled performance
and um
[Music]
basically
this is just one
uh sub argument within this section a
pro and a con
um and they're talking about essentially
skilled performance how sensory motor
models can afford sophisticated
cognitive processing
and so the first
argument here
is that here comes that same
yellow broomberg 2016 paper the
anticipating brain is not a scientist
saying that yeah actually sensory motor
loops if you're going to trust the story
for one level of analysis then why
are more so-called complex behaviors not
just more complex combinations of
modules which don't
appeal to any representational content
and then
the sensory motor dynamics created by
those models may be progressively
internalized to support mental
operations detached from a sensory
motorcycle so maybe like walking and
chewing gum or something like that or
maybe think about like an insect flying
or walking and how much of that is just
the shape of its body in motion and just
the way that the
muscles and the joints just like flex
and so ascribing the total motion of
every joint to cognitive actions
just
is probably asking too much of cognition
unless taking embodied and morphological
computation as another type of
computation
and then
um
firing back
for the representationalists
um is um
coming from the area of schema theory
which is where there is a nucleus of
sensory motor models but then they're
extended to include
external causes of sensations so that's
just kind of like a flavor of one of the
sub debates
and it'd be good to discuss i think how
the um
structural and organizational and
content related differ
because it is like a nuanced debate and
so i appreciated how clear they did make
it
given that it's murky waters because
these are like four aspects of a
philosophical idea
oh
then of course this meme
okay so
um the embodied cognition literature has
shown some practical examples of how
good control can be realized using fast
and frugal solutions and very simple
models this is an example that dave
described on a live stream just recently
one popular example is the baseball
outfielder problem or the fact that
catching a moving ball may not require a
full model of the ball's position
velocity and direction
allowing for trajectory prediction but a
simpler control mechanism that only
keeps the image of the ball stationary
on the retina
all right so
here on the left
this is like the physics
class model
of some of the parameters so this is
already a map of the territory we're not
going into the temperature of the ball
and um you know the wavelength of the
grass so this isn't like a world model
this is just the physics-reduced model
of the physics of the asymptotic ball in
this kind of idealized setting
and so that's a lot of parameters like
as drawn out there
and here from this wired article how do
people actually catch baseballs
here's the apparent ball position
as a function of time
and just showing how if if um
you're in the position to catch the ball
that there's a simple heuristic line
related to the apparent balls position
whereas
balls that you're too short or too long
to catch
um
have a very different visual trajectory
so in other words an activism
is saying
this on the left doesn't have to be the
representation
that would be something that might
satisfy
the most formal representationalist but
then this is sort of a gray area like
what if there is a visual representation
of the ball on the retina so there is
something that's featuring
information about the real world in an
actionable way
but it is of a totally different type
than
the parameters in the physics class
and so that can get of course a little
sticky so here is
us on the phillies
we're trying to catch the fly ball
here's fristen
hitting it out of the park
with the action perception loop
and all the work in this field
so
what is the equivalent
do we need to have
the physics class model
or
is it possible for us to have
some other type of understanding
just a thought what do you think blue
so it just really makes me think about
like blindness
right and i know that like this seems
like a way out there trajectory but but
like you know we know the physics of our
natural environment we know it pretty
well what about when we remove ourselves
or like remove one sense like remove
vision right now we have like a really
different
perception of our environment um and
we have to completely like retrain
through like you know kinesthetic memory
where we are in our environment if like
the lights go out i mean i was without
power for four hours the other day in
the middle of the night and i was like
totally freaked out because i live in
the country and there was absolutely no
light like none
so so in that like you have to know
where all the things are so like this is
a structural map in your mind of your
reality that's really different from
what you're able to absolutely perceive
at that moment
just makes me think of that
nice that's just a fun slide no
area slides
um
this is still on the uh uh this is i
guess on the functional aspects all
right so uh here's the functional
perspective
or the functional
aspects of representation
another way to address the issue of what
a representation is and what it is not
is by asking what functional role
representations play within a
hierarchical architecture
so this is the function
kind of the pragmatics of the
representation what it does
an idea that dates back to at least
piaget 1954
is the idea that representation should
vicariously stand for something external
in its absence
and afford vicarious operations i.e
mental operations
using an internal internal vehicle
that are executed before acting on the
external referent of the vehicle
or even when the external referent is
absent
so it is able to be
cause and effect
within the mental ecosystem
like
we'll see from these examples
consider mentally whether one would
enjoy eating a pizza with no pizza in
sight so be like okay think of a pizza
do you want to eat that now
imagine that type of food that i
previously mentioned and then what type
of restaurant it is and what equipment
do they have in the kitchen like an oven
or something like that so there's
something that's being functionally
carried forth
in that
cognitive sequence can that be
uniquely explained predicted control
designed with just sensory motor loops
this functional role of representations
has been expressed in terms of whether
the agent's internal operations are
detached from its action perception
cycle and hence autonomously generated
versus determined or sustained by
external stimuli
so if something were just repeatedly um
causing visual stimuli and that were
causing like sort of um unaware
movements
that might be one
category of phenomena
but what about going on a walk
and remembering a five-digit number
by just
chanting it to yourself
is that sensory motor how is that um
playing out and when cognition is
playing a functional role seemingly
uncoupled from the action perception
loop which is probably not exactly how
piaget framed it but that's what that
notion is
and so
within the functional aspect the fep is
leading one to ask
what functional roles do internal models
play during free energy minimization so
just like the memorizing the number was
like a cause and effect of a cognitive
environment
is it the case that the fep is featuring
things that are also causes and effects
in
the cognitive environment
and does that resemble vicarious
operations in the classical
um psja based account of representation
and again it's gonna be the dot one the
dot two when we go into the variational
and the expected free energy but that's
like the big picture on the functional
aspect
is do these variables play functional
roles
in a way that's uncoupled from the
immediacy of action and perception i
hope i represented that because i'm also
not sure about that one
okay anything to add blue
so i think about it in a different way
like you're walking down a path and
remembering a five-digit number but like
i don't know something that probably
resonates with sasha or like anybody
else that does extensive wet lab
research which you've done so it
surprises me like it doesn't bring it to
mind for you is like
thinking about your actions like it's
like a dry run of your experiments the
next day like do i have the tubes i need
the enzymes i need the reagents i need
where are all these things located like
when it's a really important experiment
like hit or miss it has to be done now
or never like which you know that there
are some that are like that
like it's important to go through and
make sure that you've got like a
cognitive represent like you build it
and so it's fresh in your mind what for
when you absolutely like execute the
experiments and so that's like instead
of walking down a path thinking of a
five-digit number how about like
planning like the the sensory motor
planning of executing a series of
experiments it brings that to mind for
me
yeah great
comment and
that
makes me think let's just say it's a one
hour experiment that you're
thinking about now does the motor
pattern
firing associated with um pushing your
thumb down on the pipet
does that get engaged
during the prospective planning of that
event
who knows to what extent but that's kind
of what's at play here if there's a
totally disjoint
neural phenomena associated with the
prospective planning then the inaction
we're in one camp of representationism i
don't even know which side of the line
anymore but then if you do have that
thumb
neural firing pattern like it's just
like sped up or just shortened or
something maybe we're in a different
area so
let's
return to these ideas because again it's
like very nuanced and it's just great
the authors laid it out
as simply as they did because this is
clearly a lot of literature to go
through
so that was the um the eight
the four times two you know that
i won't even go into it but four times
two and um
that's the bulk of the paper and then
there was this addendum section on
representation as an evolutionary
function so similar to other cognitive
functions like working memory planning
cognitive control and attention
or perhaps even to functions like flying
or swimming
representation
here intended in the sense of affording
vicarious operations and detachment from
the current action perception cycle may
be an evolutionary function
so it's kind of like when people argue
that consciousness has an adaptive role
and that the origination of
consciousness could be scaffolded or
nurtured or selected for once it arose
this is a little bit
less phenomenological
and a more cognitivist or
computationalist with respect to saying
how representation
might play an evolutionary role
so let's just imagine that there was
this detachment
between the action perception role and
planning
like here's pogonomyrex ants
imagine if they're able to
perceive the polarization of light or
the intensity of the light or the
humidity and then have something like a
representation that helps them assess
whether it's appropriate to forage on
that day
that is going to be a more adaptive nest
mate for the colony
does the colony have a representation
what level is the representation
existing at
is it
the direct target of selection or is it
arising from selection on other units
what do you think blue
like we were just talking about this
right like like so
is the niche the internet
right is that like the the meta
representation of humanity like the the
web like that's it so so i i wrote that
here and things to discuss in the dot
one or dot two is external
representation like what how do you
offload this representationalism into
the niche
awesome question and i also
um i think probably
subconsciously was thinking about that
like the image on the right is a trail
a trunk trail that the pogonomyrmex use
and so it's like it's not going in every
direction in this colony it's only going
in one direction it's along a tree so
it's kind of accentuating this natural
pattern in the generative process in the
niche but then now that is like um an
externalized
prior for foragers that's based upon the
clearing of grass and then they're less
likely to go like walk over the midden
pile and forage in a different direction
but then it does happen so the trail
does move
so it's like
interesting topics yes thanks for
writing down about the internet okay
let's continue through a few of these
last ideas
and i'm glad that we're moving briskly
through this
long paper
okay so
let's
keep thinking about that
detachment of representation from the
action perception loop
they write in other words full-fledged
decoupled representational capacities
might shade off which i wasn't even sure
what the origins were maybe it's used in
godfrey smith 96
into other cognitive or minimal
cognitive processes the dynamics of
which are increasingly more coupled to
the environment through action sensory
perception so it's like being at a level
of cognitive complexity where you can
spin up other active entities or like
the queen as a reproductive ant
is spinning off cognitive but not
reproductive nest mates
therefore when taking functional role as
contextualized by evolutionary function
as a criterion for identifying when
recourse to representation is warranted
in explanation
which is a very complex
linguistic clause
but
we're finding out when representation is
warranted
the criteria for that
would be evolution
shaping function
so it's a lot like saying nothing in
biology makes sense except in light of
evolution
and then under those settings it is
plausible to interpret at least some
processes
the ones that involve vicarious
variables
related to minimizing free energy
under
that context
the authors suggest that could drive the
kind of self-organization that fep would
describe as representational
so it's layered but it's very
fascinating because it is just like you
had said blue with
our niche
but it's like
just
stacking rocks on top of each other it's
um
resisting disorder it displays culture
but
those rocks don't have a self-modeling
capacity it's like uni direct or
uni-directional multi-scale integration
the other sims paper
whereas here we have like a human
who has part of their niche
has made
another adaptive active inference entity
and now they're engaged in this
reciprocal multi-scale integration
and so
i think the authors might be suggesting
that there's aspects of this setting
that might be described as uh
or might be warranted
to utilize representation in the
explanation
what do you think
so i wonder if this is
so i always wonder whether we should
talk about multi-scale integration
or
like thinking through other minds in
terms of translating
into the niche
and how do you like decide whether like
we're integrating as i mean i guess
there's always this thinking through
other minds aspect
of you know we leave like stigmatic
traces in like our niche environment and
and then they're picked up by other
people
or is it really multi-scale integration
like in terms of you and i are
connecting and forming a bigger unit i
always and and this is we were just
talking about this like 10 minutes
before we got here uh today so this is
something to me that's like this
fundamental paradox like i don't know
how to distinguish these two things like
we can never really
i mean i guess that shared informational
channel always comes through the niche
environment whether it's the internet or
you know some knowledge artifact like a
scientific paper or
you know a computer or something else
but like my relationship with you or any
human
is always through the niche environment
there's always that that filtration and
whether it's in real time like we are
here now
or sequentially
even if it's uh so-called in person it's
mediated by
vibrating air molecules now it's
intermediated through routers and such
it's a utilization of the niche
and i think this is just raising a super
fascinating question well yeah thanks
for raising this we'll discuss that and
then this is like saying
what it's one thing to talk through the
tin cans
that's like using the direct
um passive active inference agents um
even if we could describe the tin can as
perception in action but now what if
there's a chat bot
that's intermediating between the two of
us or it's translating between two
different languages
then
where does that put the status of that
entire cognitive system
how does it influence thinking through
other minds when the intermediaries are
passive versus adaptive active inference
entities so nice questions
all right
this is the part which also will unpack
more in the
one and two
um this is kind of the
wormhole strange loop turning the mirror
back on itself part so the authors write
in much the same manner as arriving at a
representational or non-representational
interpretation at
fep so that's the whole
sections that we just spent the whole
time on like
everything within the realm of actually
using the fep
um not taking it as an unknown but
taking the fap as an instrument and then
using it to ask whether it is
representational or not on those
different aspects so now we're gonna
put that behind us and consider
arriving at fep
as a synthesis depends on whether on
which representational criteria are
assumed
when either considering fep's central
constructs or considering specific
cognitive phenomena through the lens of
a process theory
under fep hence in the end the debate
about fep may reveal more about us
our criteria for representation and our
interests in particular facets of
cognition than it does about the
representational status of the fep
so
you know jfk is out there somewhere
ask not what the fep can do for you
it's saying
because you can be all over the map
maybe all of these sectors are in play
and all the perspectives in each of
those aspects
that means that somebody's posterior
confidence
in different
claims
is probably better reflecting of their
priors and update process
then some sort of objective stance or
consensus reality
about what the fep is
as if it could be such a thing
independent of how it's specifically
deployed
as we talked about with model-based
science and majeed benny
so this is a very
nice
point
wanna add anything blue
yeah i mean fundamentally the fvp is a
representation
right i mean it is
our representation our model i mean it
might be the one that we employ with
which to it might be an instrument or it
might be a real thing
but
still it's it it's we represent the fep
like with equations and with ideas and
memes and i don't know i mean we impute
our representation on it all the time
so whether it is a representation itself
or we represent the fep but there's some
like
there's some like
play there
it has it's integrated with
representation
um at
all the time like linguistically or
other or maybe not maybe i'm not real
uh a real an activist enough or what was
the radical radical inactivist really
radical yeah
um
well i'm sure we'll talk more about it
so just the conclusion and then a few
last points so
nine sentences in the conclusion one
they looked at four different aspects of
representation
two
understanding which side of which line
to come down on was complicated because
the fep appeals to multiple constructs
that don't
a priori seem to be strongly linked or
naturally linked like it's unclear
whether one begets the other or whether
they co-instantiate or and that's the
kind of work that we're really
interested in
in the ontology project and in the
knowledge corpus engineering of course
in the edu organizational unit of
activelab
so the fep appeals to multiple
constructs and those models
can be constructed in various ways
so
it's good to clear up representation
into these four full distinctions
however it's complex still because the
fep is kind of like a plurality in and
of itself
three they argue that depending on how
you think about things you're going to
think about things differently
they then turn the mirror back
and suggest that that's an opportunity
to challenge but it's also an
opportunity to reflect upon
how we value
representation and different features
in our model selection
related to the main part of this paper
and then they sort of salvage the
utility of fep
whether
hence fep wins
tails not fep loses
because the fep can be heuristic
so like kind of um
good for functionally or pragmatically
for a philosophy of mind
even if not so much to settle the
dispute on internal representation but
to unveil and dissect the hidden
assumptions in the debate
so it's kind of like
deploying fep into the representation
debate
it's not gonna be the judge it's gonna
be like
some other role what is the fep in that
setting
six another lesson learned
is that some traditional polarizations
might be attenuated or dissolved under
the fep
so here we're seeing multiple uses of
the fep which is why there's a bunch of
different colors on here
it's a theoretical plurality
it's as a um also a plurality of applied
models
it's a mirror
um it's a bet hedge
it's a unifier with traditional
polarizations like cognitivist versus an
activism
and then here's a really fascinating
part that i know many people in the lab
will be excited to talk about
the fep advances a unified view where
terms that traditionally belong to
different ontologies
can be harmonized
so it's an ontological unifier
for example
modeling and expectation
is not used in some of the works that
talk about autopoesis and
synchronization
eight
how does the fep do this
it begins with a strong inactivist
flavor
and a focus on action that's missing
from traditional cognitive theories
so by starting with one foot squarely in
action
it brings something that a lot of
neurocognitive theories are missing from
and then extends the scope of an
activist thinking to territories of for
example counter factual thinking and
model selection and abductive logic like
we talked about also with benny so it's
kind of like
coming from actionlandia and bringing in
inference and then starting from
inference landia and bringing in action
almost like it's called active inference
or that's like a related idea or
something and then the ninth sentence is
just saying
the space of the possible
is big
and we're going to have to reduce our
uncertainty by
making it happen
so it's a really great conclusion
any other comments on it blue
just pretty epic paper
like i think it um ties together a lot
of
stuff we've talked about stuff we will
talk about
yep
okay final things and things to discuss
in dot one and dot two
okay so here is a quote from the paper
where they say
given that fep has been implemented in a
family of computational models that are
by definition fully observable
dot dot dot that's the first part to
highlight
so in what sense are computational
models fully observable or what does
observability mean for models
what does explainability mean or
transparency mean is that
reproducibility is that perturbability
is the map fully observable
is the territory fully observable
are there settings where one or the
other or neither or both are visible
so what is this visual metaphor
and what are some of the nuances with
like observability
and visual perception
and then um here is fep as a unifier so
um
it's less surprising if one considers
fep unites notions that are generally
considered antithetical so meaning like
contrary to each other most
most notably the notion of internal
generative model which is usually
associated with representationalist
theories and autopoiesis which is
usually associated with
non-representational
inactive approaches so
i think just
um
who considers which notions antithetical
some classic examples are provided here
like to helmholtz
and matarana and varela
but just
who disagrees and why
and what can we learn by just hearing
different perspectives on some of these
debates
and then um
[Music]
how is representation related to auto
policies so
autopoetic systems are those that are
capable of producing and maintaining
themselves by creating their own parts
it's kind of a classic complexity idea
and it made me think about
poetic naturalism and then all these
other proposals like the metapoetic
naturalism and stuff
and then
there were zero google hits for
autopoetic
naturalism but i think it's very related
to
what we spoke about with majibeni
and science as modeling in the world
and about of course the title of this
paper
and um
the
uh representations
questions
so this is just a very provocative
paragraph that brings a lot of ideas in
blue
well it's also just the middle way right
like is it this or that or maybe some
combination of these two things is the
right thing
the depth perception as dean says so
then one more sort of general comment
and then we'll go to the specifics to
discuss next time so
um this is the fep as mirror
so one can use the debate on
representation and fep
the other way around not as a way to
resolve the issue at stake but as a
mirror to look at one's own implicit
notions notions of representation
so here's a paper that i wrote with my
colleague eric sovik in 2019
where we talked about scientific
theories for consciousness
and so instead of using a model of
consciousness for granted like
integrated information theory or some
other quantitative measure of
consciousness
we took the system
as the precondition which was an ant
colony
and then
reflected back on different scientific
theories of consciousness
what that said about what people value
about for example anatomical versus
functional linguistic behavioral
components of systems and so we talked
about like forward tests where you're
good with your test you've got you've
got a calibrated instrument
and so this is like what the bulk of the
literature review was in the first half
of this paper which was like we're just
gonna go with the fep as what our
framework is
and then we're going to assess there's
still a diversity of perspectives on
representation
even if you think the fep is totally the
go-to theory so this does not mean that
you eliminate ambiguity it just means
that you're using your tool in a
deployment-oriented way versus the
reverse test which is like taking things
that are known in the world or some sort
of internal reference data
and then
shining it back as a mirror
on the test and comparing amongst tests
which also does of course
recurse because it's a test being
applied to do so
but that's where the real revolutionary
science happens
and so
this
paper
by pazulo and sims
showed both modes
in
total harmony
and so i think it's an awesome
contribution from
velocity of science perspective
so i look forward to talking about that
and about forward and reverse tests and
then here's a bunch of other stuff what
are you excited about here blue
this is just stuff i wrote down to talk
about like well i was just taking notes
while we were talking today about what
might be cool to discuss in the dot one
and dot two um a lot about like the
sensory motor loop mental engagement
mental action like does that trigger the
same kind of like physiological response
as like an actual action
um and then the idea of thinking through
other minds versus multi-scale
integration what might be similar or
different there
and you know the independent existence
of the fep or is it just a mirror we
could hold up maybe for ourselves but i
think that um you know this paper was
provocative and great i um have been a
big fan of pizzula for a long time more
recently a matt sims fan but probably
i've been reading fazzullah's papers for
10 years and um
excited to have the chance to really
dissect a paper by him with with more
than just myself
great
well
glue thanks a ton for the awesome work
on the dot zero i think uh
we were trepidatious to jump into this
paper but then
you were happy
no problem i got it no i'm projecting
it's true it's true it does i was like
yeah that that's an easy yeah we got it
one week sure three days for zero we got
it we're good
so i i read a long time ago also so
um yep we just hope that anyone who
wants to ask a question
can
even if it's long past the dot 1.2 if
you're listening to this in time then
congrats and you should definitely get
involved in the conversation
and uh
otherwise we'll see you around the lab
so thanks again blue and thanks
everybody for watching see you later
thanks bye